Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers, Inclusive: 1895-1987, undated, Bulk: 1942-1953, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers
Inclusive: 1895-1987, undated, Bulk: 1942-1953, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3136
Jaworski, Dr. Hannibal "Joe" Lucas, 1902 - 1999
4 document boxes and 2 oversized folders.
The Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers include correspondence, literary productions, books, and photographic materials related to his service in World War II and his response to the Waco Tornado of 1953.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Hannibal “Joe” Lucas Jaworski was born on 1902 April 19 in Germany to Rev. Joseph and Marie Mira Jaworski. The family soon moved to Waco, Texas where his brother, Leon Jaworski, the famed Watergate lawyer, was born. Hannibal received his B.A. from Baylor University in 1921, and then went on to receive his M.D. from the Baylor Medical School in 1926. His medical residency and internship were both completed at Hillcrest Hospital in Waco.
After establishing himself as a surgeon at Hillcrest, Hannibal enlisted in the U.S. Army at the start of World War II. He was assigned to the new McClonskey General Hospital in Temple, Texas, where he eventually became Director of the Surgical Staff and achieved the rank of Colonel. During the war McClonskey was one of the Army’s largest hospitals and it was known for its outstanding orthopedic surgery, amputations, and neurosurgery. McClonskey was also a popular place for Hollywood stars to visit wounded troops. Many of the photographs, literary productions, and correspondence included in these papers were produced at McClonskey. Near the end of the war, Jaworski was transferred to the Philippines to begin preparing for an invasion of Japan. The invasion was called off after the atomic bombs were dropped. Jaworski took many photos while in the Philippines and included them in the photo album that is part of this collection.
After the war Jaworski returned to Waco and Hillcrest where he eventually became Chief of Staff. He met his future wife, Madge McReynolds when he performed successful surgery on her. The two were soon married and, despite Madge’s continual ill health, remained married for 38 years. They had no children. In 1950 Jaworski received the Carnegie Award for Heroism after rescuing a man who was drowning in the lake behind his house. At the time of the Waco Tornado, Madge and Hannibal were at his practice in downtown Waco. They were some of the first on the scene and rushed to the hospital to alert the staff of the disaster. “Dr. Joe,” as his patients called him, stayed in the hospital for nearly 24 hours treating patients. Before rushing to the hospital, Jaworski was able to take photographs of the damage that are included in these papers.
After her long illness, Madge died on 1985 December 5. By then Hannibal Jaworski was a well-known figure in the Waco community, having received from Baylor the Outstanding Service Award and the Distinguished Alumnus Award. He died on 1999 November 13. Jaworski was well respected in the community and left a legacy of care for his community and his patients. His papers will be valuable to anyone interested in studying medical care during World War II or the aftermath of the Waco Tornado.
Scope and Content
The Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers begin in 1895 and ends in 1987. The Photographic Materials series is the largest in the collection. It contains pictures pertaining to Jaworski’s service in World War II as well as the Waco Tornado of 1953. There are also several photos of 1940s celebrities as they visited patients at McClonskey General Hospital. The Literary Productions and Correspondence series include a wide range of documents relating to World War II, especially Jaworski's work as a surgeon.
The Hannibal “Joe” Lucas Jaworski Papers provide unique insight into the life of Hannibal Jaworski, United States army surgeon during World War II, long-time Waco surgeon, and witness to the Waco Tornado of 1953 May 11.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers had no organization except for one photo album. The photos were removed from the book but the original order was retained.
Currently, the Hannibal "Joe" Lucas Jaworski papers are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Books, and IV. Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3136. Acquired 1994-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Baskin, R. H., George W. Berry, George C. Bryant, M. W. Colgin, Howard R. Dudgeon, William M. Gandy, Robert K. Gassler, et al. Waco, Texas, Tornado, May 11, 1953: Monster from the Skies. Waco, TX: McLennan County Medical Society, 1991.
Newton Gresham and James A. Tinsley, "Jaworski, Leon." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 12.
Jaworski, Hannibal Joe. “Oral Memoirs of Hannibal Joe Jaworski,” 1989 June 10. Oral History Institute, Baylor University.
Jaworski, Hannibal Joe. “Waco Tornado 1953: Force that Changed the Face of Waco,” 1981 April 14. Oral History Institute, Baylor University. Accessed 2012 November 12.
“Joseph Jaworski.” Vertical File, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Ida Jo Marshall and Cheryl Ellis Vaiani, "Olin E. Teague Veterans Center, Temple." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 12.
“New Members.” Transactions of the New York Academy of Sciences 19, no. 1 (n.d.): 68-102.
Senior Class of Baylor Medical School. The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1926.
“Texas Death Records.” Roots Web. Accessed 2012 November 7.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
McCloskey General Hospital (Temple, Tex.)
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
Hospitals, Military -- history -- Texas.; Physicians -- Texas.; Tornadoes -- Texas -- Waco.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Handbooks and manuals.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1942-1946, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence relating to Hannibal Jaworski’s time as an Army surgeon during World War II. It contains letters, telegrams, and memoranda. This series is in good condition.
  - Military, 1942 June 21-October 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Military, 1943 May 26-1946 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Military: Telegrams, 1942 September 20, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military: Memoranda, 1942 April 21- September 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military: Memoranda, 1942 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Military: Memoranda, 1942 October 1- 1945 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Military: Memoranda, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Literary Productions, 1942-1987, undated; 2
  General condition: Average.
  This series includes literary productions pertaining to Hannibal Jaworski’s time as a surgeon at McClonskey Hospital during World War II, his work with the Salvation Army during and after the war, and his experience seeing the Waco Tornado. Included are issues of the Salvation Army’s “The War Cry” magazine and an unpublished copy of the McClonskey General Hospital Rules and Regulations from 1942. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Military Records: Hannibal Jaworski, 1942 May 25- 1944 December 4, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - World War II: General, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications: McClonskey Hospital, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Publications: McClonskey Hospital, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Medical Notes: General, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Medical Notes: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Medical Notes: Medical Essays, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Abdominal Injuries, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Surgery Listings, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (1 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (2 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (3 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (4 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (5 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (6 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (7 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Manuals: General Rules and Regulations: McClonskey General Hospital (8 of 8), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - “The War Cry”, 1951 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “The War Cry”, 1954 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - “The War Cry”, 1954 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - “The War Cry”, 1960 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - “The War Cry”, 1961 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - “The War Cry”, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Printed Materials: Salvation Army, 1943-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clippings, 1943-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clippings, 1944-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Clippings, 1967-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1972-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Programs: Dachau Concentration Camp, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Printed Materials: Waco Tornado, 1953 May 22-1981 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General, 1942-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publications: “The Yank Army Weekly”: VE Issue, 1945 June 1 (Box [1065] OVZ, Folder 4)
- Books, 1895-1964; 3
  This series contains books from Hannibal Jaworski’s library. It includes a signed copy of Memoirs of James A. Bethea and an annotated copy of English Essays by Walter C. Bronson. This series is in good condition.
  - English Essays by Walter C. Bronson, annotated, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A New History of Texas by Percy V. Pennybacker, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Memoirs of James A. Bethea by James A. Bethea, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Loose Materials: Christmas Letter: James Bethea, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographic Materials, 1944-1953, undated; 4
  This series, the largest in the Hannibal “Joe” Lucas Jaworski Papers contains pictures pertaining to Jaworski’s service in World War II as well as the Waco Tornado of 1953. Included in the war photos are many pictures of the McClonskey General Hospital surgical ward, surgeries in progress, soldiers on a transport train, and wounded soldiers with various movie stars of the 1940s (see list of stars below). Most of these photos were removed from a large undated photo album exclusively containing war photos. The tornado photos are unique in that they were taken in the immediate aftermath of the storm and the slides are rare color images of the destruction.
  Stars Included in Photo Album-
  Name: Photo Album Page Number
  Betty Alexander: 120
  Gene Autrey: 46-49
  Leslie Brooks 118
  Ginny Simms: 54
  Trudy Marshall: 119
  Lynn Merrick: 120
  Harold Russell: 98-100, 124
  Frank Sully: 118
  This series is in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  35 mm slide; Photographic print; Portrait photograph
  - Waco Tornado (1 of 2), 1953 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Waco Tornado (2 of 2), 1953 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Color Slides: Waco Tornado, 1953 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Medical Photos, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - McClonskey Hospital: Surgical, 1944 January 25, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - McClonskey Hospital: General, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Army Transport Train, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Military Group Pictures, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Military (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Military (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Shirley Temple Stock Photo, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photo Album: Page 1-2, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photo Album: Page 3-4, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photo Album: Page 5-6, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photo Album: Page 7-8, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photo Album: Page 9-10, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photo Album: Page 11-12, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photo Album: Page 13-14, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photo Album: Page 15-16, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photo Album: Page 17-21, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photo Album: Page 22-27, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photo Album: Page 28-33, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photo Album: Page 34-37, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photo Album: Page 38-41, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photo Album: Page 42-45, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photo Album: Page 46-49, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photo Album: Page 50-53, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photo Album: Page 54-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photo Album: Page 58-61, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photo Album: Page 62-65, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photo Album: Page 66-69, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photo Album: Page 70-73, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Photo Album: Page 74-77, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photo Album: Page 78-81, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photo Album: Page 82-85, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photo Album: Page 86-89, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photo Album: Page 90-93, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photo Album: Page 94-97, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photo Album: Page 98-101, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photo Album: Page 102-105, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photo Album: Page 106-109, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photo Album: Page 110-113, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photo Album: Page 114-117, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photo Album: Page 118-121, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photo Album: Page 122-125, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photo Album: Page 126-129, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photo Album: Page 130-133, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photo Album: Page 134-138, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, undated (Box [1065] OVZ, Folder 5)